Guide to the KVOS Channel 12 Film Records 1961-1967
Western Washington University, Heritage Resources
- Channel 12 Specials, 1962-1967; Series II
  - S-32 Our Public Schools (Elizabeth Kuntz), 1964 August 20 (Box-reel 25/2)
    Description: North Carolina special education teacher Elizabeth Kuntz is interviewed by Al Swift. Kuntz, then president elect of the Department of Classroom Teachers of the National Education Association, talks about a wide range of issues related to teaching, education, and educational philosophy. Segregation, desegregation, and racial integration in southern schools are discussed at length, with an emphasis on equal opportunity for black children. Other key topics include the evolution of the teaching profession, and the relationship between teachers, administrators, and the community. Kuntz was in Bellingham to attend the 1964 Annual Classroom Teachers National Conference. A commercial advertisement for CARE USA, an international relief organization, precedes the interview. A commercial advertisement for the National Council on Alcoholism, featuring Robert Young and Marty Mann, interrupts the interview two minutes before the end.
  - S-33 Potpourri: Bells and Whidbey Naval Air Station, 1964 September 3 (Box-reel 25/3)
    Length: 12:40 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): fair (fragments, scraps)
    Description: This entirely silent reel features a mishmash of unrelated, out of context footage on two subjects: sports, and jet aircraft at the Whidbey Naval Air Station. A baseball game and football practice comprise the first category; while uniforms are labeled Giants and Jets, it is clear that this is not footage of the famous teams bearing those names. The airplane shots include at least two types of Naval jets; both believed to be bombers. One might be an F-4 Phantom II, and is shown maneuvering in flight. Footage lacks explanatory context
  - S-36 The Natural World Of Poetry (Bob Huff and Knute Skinner), 1965 January 21 (Box-reel 26/1)
    Length: 20:30 minutes
    Description: Western Washington University English Professors Robert Huff and Knute Skinner read a number of short poems aloud throughout this episode. Some of Huff’s own work that he reads includes the poems Rainbow and Dying Dentist. Skinner’s selections include his poems Park, Pillow, Swirl, and The Lion. Additionally, both poets read the works of other poets, including Walt Whitman, William Butler Yates, and Gerard Manley Hopkins.
  - S-37 Intalco: A Visit from Paris, 1965 February 18 (Box-reel 26/2)
    Description: Several people (unidentified), both French and American, discuss the new INTALCO Aluminum plant being built in Ferndale. Issues include site selection, growth and development, freight rates, tax incentives, energy rates, and pollution. One spokesperson promises that the smelter will be a good corporate neighbor, installing equipment to minimize pollutants through fume control. Fragmentary footage; lacks contextual information. See S-26 for more on Whatcom County’s efforts to attract industrial development and private enterprise to the area
  - S-38 The Seventh President (Harvey Bunke), 1965 February 25 (Box-reel 27/1)
    Length: 16:30 minutes
    Sound: yes (inconsistent quality)
    Description: This reel contains most of the inauguration speech made by the seventh president of Western Washington University (formerly Western Washington State College). In addition to outlining his educational philosophy (with a focus on higher education), Bunke emphasizes equality of opportunity through public education. He outlines his goals for his administration; amongst other things, he pledges a commitment to general education, upholding the value of individuality, and landscaping. Fragmentary footage, incomplete
  - S-39A Report from Olympia, 1965 March 18 (Box-reel 27/2)
    Description: Footage of interviews with several unnamed people in Olympia, following passage of the 1965 Washington State Budget. Interviewees discuss the implications of the budget to Whatcom County, with a focus on Western Washington University, which had its funding cut. There is some speculation as to whether a recent peace march affected this decision, but the interviewees deny that the demonstration had anything to do with it. The proposed Alaska Ferry Marine Highway terminus in Bellingham is also discussed. Fragmentary footage, incomplete
  - S-39 The Color of Black, 1965 April 15 (Box-reel 28/1)
    Film Quality (Original): good (footage ends abruptly)
    Description: Civil Rights leader and activist James Farmer is interviewed for the entire episode. Farmer, founding member and head of the Congress of Racial Equality, or CORE, discusses a wide range of issues related to the Civil Rights movement, including segregation, desegregation, racial discrimination, the protest movement, nonviolent protest, the freedom riders, the marches on Selma and Montgomery, President Lyndon Johnson, and Alabama Governor George Wallace. He contrasts the black movements in the north with those in the south, and describes an overall “negro revolution.” He relates a powerful story of his own recent escape from a violent lynch mob of Louisiana State Troopers and police in Plaquemine, Louisiana. He describes what a cattle prod feels like.
  - S-40 The Road to Redress, 1965 April 22 (Box-reel 29/1)
    Length: 18:40 minutes
    Sound: yes (poor quality recording during speech).
    Description: A Bellingham peace protest march against the Vietnam War is captured. Protesters carry signs and placards against the war, featuring slogans such as “Negotiation Not Napalm.” More attention is devoted on this reel to the much smaller group of counter-protesters, who favor the war; one spokesperson is interviewed for several minutes. Their slogans include “draft the pacifists.” Some of the anti-war demonstration takes place in front of the Hotel Leopold. The second half of the reel is taken up by an unidentified man giving a speech about the Vietnam War; the audio is poor, and it is difficult to make out much of the speech. See also 13-1 for more Bellingham area protest footage
  - S-41 Mr. Justice Douglas, Undated (Box-reel 29/2)
    Description: Supreme Court Justice William O. Douglas is interviewed for the half-hour episode. Douglas, a native of Yakima, WA, and a former dean of law at Yale, was then serving his 26th year on the bench. He discusses a wide range of topics, including freedom of the press, rights of the accused, Lee Harvey Oswald and the Kennedy assassination, the constitution and constitutional issues, segregation, states rights, and citizen’s equal rights to the due process of law. Douglas compares the court under three different Chief Justices: Harlan Fiske Stone, Frederick Moore Vinson, and Earl Warren. He also mentions his commitment to wilderness conservation, highlighted by his 1958 efforts to raise awareness about the Olympic Peninsula coast. He closes with a short commentary about China and Chinese relations. Douglas had been appointed to the court by Franklin Delano Roosevelt in 1939.
  - S-43 Let the Chips Fall, 1965 July 1 (Box-reel 29/3)
    Length: 11:30 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): film requires several splices.
    Sound: partial (first five minutes lack sound)
    Description: Scenes from the 1965 Deming Log Show. Lumberjack and logging themed competitions are captured, including contests involving the use of saws, chainsaws, floating logs, and axes. Two contestants, both professional speed climbers, are interviewed about the sport of speed climbing.
  - S-46A And Have Not Love, 1965 October 3 (Box-reel 30/1)
    Duplicate: VHS, DVD, other reels of film
    Description: This episode highlights Project Overcome: An Experiment in Education. Fifty disadvantaged and poverty-stricken high school students from Washington State urban slums and Indian Reservations were chosen to participate in the pilot program at Western Washington State College (later Western Washington University). The camera follows them through eight rigorous summer weeks of classroom instruction, communal living, and educational field trips. The students were housed in the Ridgeway Residences, took meals in the Viking Union, and studied with many professors and instructors, including biologist Jerry Flora, Bellingham artist Leland Stanley, writer Don McCloud, and others. The film highlights the students singing a folksong with history professor Jack Trailer, as well as a student art exhibit. Field trips included the Bellingham Highland Games, Victoria, the Lakewood property on Lake Whatcom, and a Mt. Baker hike. Project Overcome was part of Upward Bound, and was supported by the Office of Economic Opportunity. S-46B is a duplicate of the same episode
  - S-46B And Have Not Love, 1965 October 3 (Box-reel 30/2)
    Duplicate: VHS, DVD, other reels of film.
    Description: see S-46A (duplicate reel). Duplicate of S-46A
  - S-48 Dick Gregory, 1966 February 13 (Box-reel 31/1)
    Length: 27:15 minutes
    Description: Black stand-up comic, entertainer, author, nutritionist, and civil rights activist Dick Gregory, then famous for his anti-establishment satire, is interviewed in this episode. Although the interviewer (unidentified) calls Gregory America’s “foremost negro comedian,” Gregory comments upon a range of serious topics relating to the civil rights movement. Gregory, who had been shot in the leg during the August 1965 Watts Riots in Los Angeles (during which 32 people were killed), discusses segregation, recent civil rights legislation, Martin Luther King, local and regional black leaders, the philosophy of the protest movement, protests, nonviolence, pacifism, and social justice in America. Gregory emphasizes the simmering tensions in oppressed minority communities. This reel also contains two public service announcement commercials. The advertisement preceding the episode is an animation cartoon produced by the American Dental Association, and promotes fluoride and fluoridation as a solution to tooth decay. The ad following the episode, produced by the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, promotes clean water – and cites a growing problem of pollution and contamination.
  - S-49 A Place Called Home, 1966 March 20 (Box-reel 31/2)
    Length: 10:40 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): Poor. Reel needs dozens of splices (if it is deemed important enough to bother with).
    Description: Reel composed of outtakes and scraps of footage from an episode not represented in this collection. The footage focuses on elderly housing, showing the poor condition of low-income senior housing. There is also some low-quality footage of the city of Bellingham. All footage lacks sound and is fragmentary. See S-56 for slightly better footage of these issues. Footage is devoid of context
  - S-52 Guemes Island: Beginning or End?, 1966 September 11 (Box-reel 32/1)
    Length: 23:45 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): good (but requires a few splices)
    Description: This episode concerns the 1966 attempt by Northwest Aluminum Company to build an Aluminum plant on Guemes Island, one of the San Juan Islands. Although favored by Skagit County and then economically depressed Anacortes, residents of Guemes Island almost uniformly opposed the plan, and formed a citizen’s action group, “Save the San Juans,” led by retired Boeing executive Evan Nelson. Nelson hired a young John Erlichman (pre-Nixon) as the group’s lawyer. Although Skagit County hastily rezoned a portion of the island for heavy industry, in 1967 the corporation bowed to public pressure and withdrew from this attempt. The film features short interviews with people in favor of and opposed to the proposed industrial development (all except Nelson are unidentified). In addition, there is a small amount of scenic footage. See S-53 for more about this issue. See S-36 for footage concerning the INTALCO Aluminum plant in Ferndale, WA
  - S-53 Guemes Island: View From Anacortes, 1966 September 18 (Box-reel 32/2)
    Length: 24:30 minutes
    Description: This reel consists of a press conference by an executive spokesperson from Northwest Aluminum Company. The spokesperson (unidentified) explains why the Guemes Island site was chosen, and describes the company’s plan for development. Northwest Aluminum, a subsidiary of a Japanese-backed consortium, sought a deep water site with adjacent flat acreage, and was also lured by the promise of cheap power from Bonneville power. Despite Skagit County’s hasty rezoning of the area to heavy industrial, public opposition forced the company to withdraw the next year. See S-52 for more on this issue, and S-36 for footage concerning the INTALCO aluminum plant in Ferndale (Whatcom County)
  - S-56 Low Cost Housing, Undated (Box-reel 33/1)
    Length: 23:30 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): fair
    Description: Reel of footage concerning affordable housing for low-income elderly in Bellingham. At 13:30 minutes there is a short interview with a Mrs. Howell of Bellingham, a seventy-year old resident of government subsidized housing. At 19:15 minutes there is a short interview with an unidentified official who claims that Bellingham is well ahead of federal standards in this area, and refers to urban renewal. There is also some silent aerial footage and scenic footage of Bellingham. Most of the reel consists of scraps and fragmented footage, lacking sound and context
  - S-57 North to the Future: Alaskan Ferry, Undated (Box-reel 33/2)
    Length: 41 minutes.
    Film Quality (Original): fair – film requires several splices.*
    Description: This reel of film concerns the proposed marine highway link between Alaska and Washington State. The reel consists of both color and black and white footage, and includes both magnetic and optical film spliced together. There are several interviews with newly-elected Alaskan Governor Walter Joseph Hickel, during which he promotes the ferry, and describes transportation problems concerning Alaska. He criticizes the Jones Act, which requires domestic cargo to be transported on American vessels. A representative of the Bellingham Terminal Committee (unidentified) presents the case for a Bellingham terminus; at the time, Seattle and Anacortes were also under consideration. There is silent color footage both of and from the ferry Matanuska, including the Sehome High School Band (Bellingham) performing on its deck. Scenic footage from the ferry includes Seattle (Space Needle visible), and arrival in Ketchikan.
    Note: *VHS and DVD copies may exhibit brief inconsistencies in sound, quality, due to switches between optical and magnetic film on the reel
  - S-60 Interview With John J. O'Connell, 1967 August 27 (Box-reel 34/1)
    Length: 25:45 minutes
    Description: Washington State Attorney General John J. O’Connell is interviewed in this episode. O’Connell begins by discussing the “long hot summer” of race riots which occurred in many U.S. cities that year, and explains why a race riot was unlikely to occur in Washington State. He discusses the social tensions and injustices which led to these outbreaks of chaos and violence, and talks about fair housing legislation. He also mentions, in passing, the similar injustices faced by Native Americans. Next, O’Connell explores the broader topic of soaring crime rates, both nationally and state-wide. He suggests a need to reexamine ineffective punitive measures against crime. Finally, O’Connell calls for major reform of the Washington State Constitution; including a complete constitutional re-write, to be undertaken by a constitutional convention of elected delegates.
  - S-61 Bellingham Technical School, Undated (Box-reel 34/2)
    Description: Bellingham Technical School (precursor of Bellingham Technical College) is profiled in this episode. After an introduction by Western Washington University President Harvey Bunke, Citizen’s Education Committee chairman David Mintz discusses the benefits of non-traditional education, embodied by the vocational school. The technical school offered a wide range of programs, including nursing, engineering, electronics, mechanics, and cooking. Footage of the cafeteria shows culinary students preparing and serving meals, while students in the carpentry shop and machine shop gained experience in those professions. Mr. Pratt, and engineering technology instructor, is briefly interviewed about surveying and drafting.
  - S-64 He Would Be Dead Now (Outtakes), 1967 August 27 (Box-reel 34/3)
    Film Quality (Original): good (scraps)
    Description: Six minutes of color footage outtakes from an episode not represented in the collection. The subject is a young Nooksack tribal member (identified only as Roy Jr.) who is undergoing dialysis treatments at the Seattle Artificial Kidney center. The footage includes excerpts of the treatment underway, a description of the anticoagulant drug used in the process, and part of an interview with Roy himself. The last minute or so features his father, who discusses the need to bring a dialysis machine to the Everson – Nooksack area. Color footage
  - S-65 A Place to Grow, 1967 September 17 (Box-reel 35/1)
    Description: This full-length color episode profiles Latino migrant farm workers in Skagit County, and some new programs designed to help them and their children. Called “Spanish Americans” in the film, these migrant laborers are present for several weeks each year in Skagit County, harvesting strawberries, raspberries, cucumbers, etc. A group called the Skagit Migrant Facilities Committee was particularly focused on providing limited educational and community opportunities for the children of the workers, who are described in the film as “functional illiterates.” The committee, under its president William Grant (a Methodist Minister) obtained funds through the Washington State Office of Economic Opportunity and from charitable donations. One of two daycare centers funded by the group was at the Immaculate Conception School in Mount Vernon; a second center was located in Burlington. Both sought to address the issues of illiteracy and cultural alienation, and offered bilingual instruction in both English and Spanish. Color footage
  - S-66 Junk Mail, 1967 October 1 (Box-reel 35/2)
    Length: 15 minutes
    Description: Deputy Postmaster General Frederick C. Beeley (sp?) is interviewed about junk mail, mass-mailings, bulk advertising, improving post office service, and the suggested postal rate increase. He discusses first class, second class, third class, and fourth class (parcel post) mail. Lawrence O’Brien was then Postmaster General. Black and white footage
  - S-67 Western's Fourth R, 1967 October 15 (Box-reel 36/1)
    Description: A diverse array of Western Washington University faculty members involved in research are profiled. The first four minutes are silent, and feature Professor Gerald Kraft and students conducting field experiments from a boat. After that a series of professors explain their research. These include Dr. June Ross, one of the first female biochemists at the University, who discusses her research on sponges. Ross is the wife of Geology Professor Charles Ross. Dr. Larry Douglas talks about monitoring the impact of special educational programs in minority neighborhoods. Dr. Carol Diers from the psychology department, a specialist in personality research, discusses a failed experiment involving armadillos (the last armadillo died from exposure to Bellingham’s climate). Dr. Debnath Mookhergee of the geography department explains his research into urban demographics in India. Dr. Joseph Hashisaki of the math department highlights his book, The Theory of Arithmetic. The last few minutes of footage feature local saltwater invertebrates, including crabs, sea urchins, and sea cucumbers. The bizarre looking Puget Sound King Crab (Lopholithodes mandtii) is included.
  - S-68 Christmas Concert: The Sehome Choir, 1967 December 24 (Box-reel 36/2)
    Length: 28: 30 minutes
    Description: This color episode features the 1967 Christmas Concert performed by the Sehome High School choir. Several songs, Christmas carols, and Hymns are performed, with brief commentary.
  - S-69 Julian Bond Interview., 1967 May 18 (Box-reel 36/3)
    Film Quality (Original): good (but abrupt ending; cut off)
    Description: Georgia State Legislator and Anti Vietnam War activist Julian Bond is interviewed in front of the Old Main building at Western Washington University. Political Science Department Chairman Manfred Vernon also participated in the discussion. The discussion focuses heavily on the war in Vietnam, and topics include pacifism, the draft and conscription, unilateral withdrawal, poverty, racism, race relations, minorities, civil rights, political activism, and Dr. Martin Luther King. Bond, then a 27 year old African-American, had to fight for two years in the Supreme Court before the State of Georgia would recognize the legitimacy of his victory. The following year, as a delegate to the infamous 1968 Democratic convention in Chicago, he was a key member of the “Georgia Loyalist” faction. He is currently (2005) the Chairman of the NAACP.
  - Reach Out! (AAUW), undated (Box-reel 36/4)
    Length: 12 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): fair (color severely faded)
    Description: This American Association of University Women promotional film focuses on the Educational Fellowship Foundation Program, which gives grants to women studying at the pre-doctoral, doctoral, and post-doctoral levels. It also supports independent research. Film is produced and distributed by Pilgrim Film Services. An AAUW Endowment Promotional Film
  - (Box 37)
    Description: This box contains the Alpha and Beta Master tapes for the films in Box 30 "Have Not Love" as well as a Master Audio track on 16mm Film.
  - (Boxes 38-43)
    Description:These boxes contain all the VHS Tape and DVD copies of the above KVOS films.